Throughout my career, I've been fortunate enough
طوال حياتي المهنية، كنت محظوظاً بما فيه الكفاية
to work with many of the great
للعمل مع العديد من أعظم
international architects,
المهندسين المعماريين العالميين،
documenting their work and observing
أوثق عملهم وأراقب
how their designs have the capacity
كيف أن لتصاميمهم القدرة
to influence the cities in which they sit.
علي التأثير على المدن التي بنيت فيها.
I think of new cities like Dubai
أفكر في المدن الجديدة مثل دبي
or ancient cities like Rome
أو المدن الأثرية مثل روما
with Zaha Hadid's incredible MAXXI museum,
مع متحف ماكسي الرائع من تصميم زاها حديد،
or like right here in New York with the High Line,
أو هنا مثل حديقة الهاى لاين في نيويورك،
a city which has been so much influenced
و هي مدينة تأثرت كثيراً
by the development of this.
بتطوير هذا المشروع.
But what I find really fascinating
لكن ما أجده رائعاً حقاً
is what happens when architects and planners leave
هو ما يحدث عندما يغادر المهندسين المعماريين والمخططين
and these places become appropriated by people,
و يستولي الناس على هذه الأماكن،
like here in Chandigarh, India,
مثل هنا في شانديغار، الهند،
the city which has been completely designed
المدينة التي تم تصميمها بالكامل
by the architect Le Corbusier.
من قبل المهندس المعماري لي كوربيزير.
Now 60 years later, the city has been taken over
الآن بعد مرور 60 عاماً، قد تم الاستيلاء على المدينة
by people in very different ways
من قبل الناس بطرق مختلفة جداً
from whatever perhaps intended for,
مما قُصد من بناؤها،
like here, where you have the people
مثل هنا، حيث لديك الناس
sitting in the windows of the assembly hall.
يجلسون على نوافذ قاعة الجمعية.
But over the course of several years,
ولكن على مدى عدة سنوات،
I've been documenting Rem Koolhaas's
لقد كنت أوثق لريم كولهاس
CCTV building in Beijing
مبنى تلفزيون الصين المركزي (CCTV) في بكين
and the olympic stadium in the same city
والأستاد الأولمبي في نفس المدينة
by the architects Herzog and de Meuron.
من تصميم المعماريين هيرزوغ ودي ميرون.
At these large-scale construction sites in China,
في مواقع البناء الضخمة هذه،
you see a sort of makeshift camp
ترى ما يشبه المخيم المؤقت
where workers live during the entire building process.
حيث يعيش العمال خلال عملية البناء بأكملها.
As the length of the construction takes years,
و بما أن البناء يستغرق سنوات،
workers end up forming a rather rough-and-ready
فينتهي المطاف بتكوين العمال لمدينة غير رسمية
informal city, making for quite a juxtaposition
بسيطة و جاهزة، مما يشكل تناقض واضح
against the sophisticated structures that they're building.
مع الأبنية الراقية التي يبنوها.
Over the past seven years, I've been following
خلال السنوات السبع الماضية، لقد كنت أتبع
my fascination with the built environment,
انبهاري بالبيئة المبنية،
and for those of you who know me, you would say
و هؤلاء الذين يعرفوني، قد يقولوا
that this obsession has led me to live
أن هذا الهوس قد قادني إلى
out of a suitcase 365 days a year.
الترحال المستمر 365 يوم في السنة.
Being constantly on the move
إن التنقل المستمر
means that sometimes I am able
يعني أنني قادر أحياناً
to catch life's most unpredictable moments,
على انتهاز أكثر لحظات الحياة عفوية،
like here in New York
مثل هنا في نيويورك
the day after the Sandy storm hit the city.
بعد يوم من عاصفة ساندي التي ضربت المدينة.
Just over three years ago,
منذ حوالي ثلاثة سنين،
I was for the first time in Caracas, Venezuela,
سافرت لأول مرة إلى كاراكاس، في فنزويلا،
and while flying over the city, I was just amazed
و بالطيران فوق المدينة، كنت مبهوراً
by the extent to which the slums
بالمدى الذي تمتد فيه
reach into every corner of the city,
الأحياء الفقيرة في كل ركن من أركان المدينة،
a place where nearly 70 percent of the population
المدينة التي يعيش حوالي 70 بالمئة من سكانها
lives in slums,
في الأحياء الفقيرة،
draped literally all over the mountains.
تغطي حرفياً كل مكان على الجبال.
During a conversation with local architects Urban-Think Tank,
من خلال حديث مع مهندسين معماريين محليين من مكتب أربان-ثنك تانك،
I learned about the Torre David,
قد عرفت بتوري ديفيد &amp;quot;برج داوود&amp;quot;،
a 45-story office building which sits
و هو مبنى للمكاتب مكون من 45 طابق
right in the center of Caracas.
في قلب مدينة كاراكاس.
The building was under construction
لقد كان المبنى قيد الإنشاء
until the collapse of the Venezuelan economy
حتى انهيار الاقتصاد الفنزولي
and the death of the developer in the early '90s.
و وفاة المطوّر في بداية التسعينيات.
About eight years ago, people started moving
منذ حوالي ثمانية سنوات، بدأ الناس في الانتقال
into the abandoned tower
للبرج المهجور
and began to build their homes right in between
و بدأوا ببناء منازلهم بين
every column of this unfinished tower.
أعمدة هذا البناء الغير مكتمل.
There's only one little entrance to the entire building,
يوجد مدخل واحد صغير للبناء كله،
and the 3,000 residents come in and out
و يدخل و يخرج ال3,000 ساكن
through that single door.
من خلال هذا الباب الوحيد.
Together, the inhabitants created public spaces
سوياً، كوّن السكّان مساحات عامّة
and designed them to feel more like a home
و صمموها لتعطي شعوراً بأنها منزل
and less like an unfinished tower.
أكثر مما هي برج غير مكتمل البناء.
In the lobby, they painted the walls and planted trees.
في الردهة، قاموا بدهن الحوائط و بزراعة الأشجار.
They also made a basketball court.
قاموا أيضاً بإنشاء ملعب لكرة السلة.
But when you look up closely,
لكن عندما تنظر عن قرب،
you see massive holes where elevators
تجد ثقوب ضخمة حيث كان من المخطط للمصاعد
and services would have run through.
و الخدمات أن تمر من خلالها.
Within the tower, people have come up
داخل البرج، قام الناس بإيجاد
with all sorts of solutions
كل أنواع الحلول
in response to the various needs
للاستجابة للحاجات المتنوعة
which arise from living in an unfinished tower.
التي تنشأ نتيجة للعيش في برج غير مكتمل البناء.
With no elevators,
من دون المصاعد،
the tower is like a 45-story walkup.
يتوجب على الناس الصعود 45 طابق على الأقدام.
Designed in very specific ways
تم تصميمه بطرق محددة جداً
by this group of people
من قبل هذه المجموعة من الناس
who haven't had any education in architecture or design.
التي لم تتلقى أي تعليم في هندسة العمارة أو التصميم.
And with each inhabitant finding their own
و مع إيجاد كل ساكن
unique way of coming by,
طريقته الخاصة للتأقلم،
this tower becomes like a living city,
أصبح هذا البناء مثل المدينة الحيوية،
a place which is alive with micro-economies
مكان حيّ له اقتصاده المصغّر
and small businesses.
و أعماله التجارية الصغيرة.
The inventive inhabitants, for instance,
السكان المبدعين، على سبيل المثال،
find opportunities in the most unexpected cases,
يجدون الفرصة في أقل الحالات توقعاً،
like the adjacent parking garage,
كموقف السيارات المجاور،
which has been reclaimed as a taxi route
الذي تم استخدامه كطريق لسيارات الأجرة
to shuttle the inhabitants up through the ramps
لنقل السكان إلى أعلى المنحدرات
in order to shorten the hike
لتقليل مسافة الصعود
up to the apartments.
للأعلى إلى الشقق.
A walk through the tower
إن السير في البرج
reveals how residents have figured out
يكشف كيف تدبّر السكان
how to create walls, how to make an air flow,
إنشاء جدران، عمل تهوية،
how to create transparency,
تكوين شفافية،
circulation throughout the tower,
تدوير خلال البرج،
essentially creating a home
أي إنشاء منزل
that's completely adapted
متكيف تماماً
to the conditions of the site.
مع ظروف المكان.
When a new inhabitant moves into the tower,
عندما ينتقل ساكن جديد للبرج،
they already have a roof over their head,
يجد سقفاً موجود سلفاً فوق رأسه،
so they just typically mark their space
لذا هو يحدد مكانه فقط
with a few curtains or sheets.
بعدة ستائر أو أغطية.
Slowly, from found materials, walls rise,
تدريجياً، من المواد الموجودة، يتم إنشاء الجدران،
and people create a space out of any found objects
و يكوّن الناس مساحة مما يجدونه من أشياء
or materials.
أو مواد.
It's remarkable to see the design decisions
إن النظر إلى القرارات التي يتخذونها في التصميم
that they're making,
لأمر مثير للاهتمام،
like when everything is made out of red bricks,
مثلاً حينما يكون كل شيء مصنوع من القرميد الأحمر،
some residents will cover that red brick
يقوم بعض السكان بتغطية هذا القرميد الأحمر
with another layer of red brick-patterned wallpaper
بطبقة أخرى من ورق الحائط ذات نقش القرميد الأحمر
just to make it a kind of clean finish.
فقط لجعل اللمسة النهائية أنظف.
The inhabitants literally built up these homes
إن السكان قاموا حرفياً ببناء هذا المنازل
with their own hands, and this labor of love
بأيديهم، و هذا العمل المدفوع بالحب
instills a great sense of pride
يغرس شعوراً كبير بالفخر
in many families living in this tower.
في الكثير من العائلات التي تعيش في هذا البرج.
They typically make the best out of their conditions,
إنهم يتدبرون أمورهم بأفضل طريقة ممكنة بالنظر إلى ظروفهم،
and try to make their spaces look nice and homey,
و يحاولون جعل مساحاتهم تبدو جميلة و دافئة،
or at least up until as far as they can reach.
أو على الأقل بقدر الإمكان.
Throughout the tower, you come across
خلال البرج، تصادف
all kinds of services, like the barber,
كل أنواع الخدمات، كالحلاق،
small factories, and every floor has
مصانع صغيرة، و لكل طابق
a little grocery store or shop.
بقالة صغيرة أو محل.
And you even find a church.
و يمكنك حتى إيجاد كنيسة.
And on the 30th floor, there is a gym
و في الطابق الثلاثين، يوجد نادي رياضي
where all the weights and barbells
حيث كل الأوزان و الأثقال
are made out of the leftover pulleys
مصنوعة من البكرات المتبقية
from the elevators which were never installed.
من المصاعد التي لم يتم تركيبها أبدأ.
From the outside, behind this always-changing facade,
من الخارج، وراء واجهة المبنى هذه المتغيرة باستمرار،
you see how the fixed concrete beams
ترى كيف توفر الأعمدة الخرسانية المصبوبة
provide a framework for the inhabitants
هيكل للسكان
to create their homes
لصنع منازلهم
in an organic, intuitive way
بطريقة عضوية، و بديهية
that responds directly to their needs.
تستجيب مباشرة لحاجاتهم.
Let's go now to Africa, to Nigeria,
الآن دعنا ننتقل إلى أفريقيا، إلى نيجيريا،
to a community called Makoko,
إلى مجتمع يسمى بماكوكو،
a slum where 150,000 people
هو حي فقير حيث يعيش 150,000 شخص
live just meters above the Lagos Lagoon.
فقط بضعة أميال فوق بحيرة لاجوس.
While it may appear to be a completely chaotic place,
بينما قد يبدو مكان فوضوي كلياً،
when you see it from above, there seems to be
عندما تراه من الأعلى، يبدو أنه يوجد
a whole grid of waterways and canals
شبكة متكاملة من مجاري المياه و الأقنية المائية
connecting each and every home.
تصل كل بيت.
From the main dock, people board long wooden canoes
من المرسى الرئيسي، يركب الناس مراكب خشبية طويلة
which carry them out to their various homes and shops
التي تحملهم إلى منازلهم و محلاتهم التجارية
located in the expansive area.
الموجودة في المنطقة الممتدة.
When out on the water, it's clear
عند الخروج إلى الماء، إنه واضح
that life has been completely adapted
أن الحياة تم تكييفها بالكامل
to this very specific way of living.
لتتلاءم مع طريقة العيش هذه تحديداً.
Even the canoes become variety stores
حتى الزوارق أصبحت متاجر لبضائع متنوعة
where ladies paddle from house to house,
حيث تجدف السيدات من بيت إلى آخر،
selling anything from toothpaste to fresh fruits.
تبعن أشياء متنوعة من معجون الأسنان إلى الفواكه الطازجة.
Behind every window and door frame,
وراء كل هيكل نافذة و باب،
you'll see a small child peering back at you,
سوف تجد طفل صغير يحدق إليك،
and while Makoko seems to be packed with people,
و بينما تبدو ماكوكو مزدحمة بالناس،
what's more shocking is actually
الأمر الذي يبدو أكثر غرابة بالحقيقة
the amount of children pouring out of every building.
هو عدد الأطفال الذين ينبعون من كل مبنى.
The population growth in Nigeria,
إن النمو السكاني في نيجيريا،
and especially in these areas like Makoko,
و خصوصاً في هذه المناطق كماكوكو،
are painful reminders
يذكرنا بقسوة
of how out of control things really are.
بالدرجة الحقيقية لخروج الأمور عن السيطرة.
In Makoko, very few systems
في ماكوكو، يوجد القليل جداً من الأنظمة
and infrastructures exist.
و البنية التحتية.
Electricity is rigged and freshest water
إن الكهرباء لا تعمل و مصدر الماء العذبة
comes from self-built wells throughout the area.
هو آبار حفرها الناس في المنطقة.
This entire economic model
هذا النموذج الاقتصادي بأكمله
is designed to meet a specific way of living
صمم ليلبّي طريقة معينة للمعيشة
on the water, so fishing and boat-making
على الماء، لذا فإن صيد السمك و صناعة السفن
are common professions.
تعد مهن رائجة.
You'll have a set of entrepreneurs
سوف تجد مقاولين
who have set up businesses throughout the area,
قد أسسوا أعمال تجارية في المنطقة،
like barbershops, CD and DVD stores,
مثل محلات حلاقة، محلات لبيع الCD و DVD،
movie theaters, tailors, everything is there.
مسارح السينما، خياطين، كل شيء موجود.
There is even a photo studio
يوجد حتى استديو تصوير
where you see the sort of aspiration
حيث يمكنك أن ترى الطموح
to live in a real house or to be associated
للعيش في بيت حقيقي أو في
with a faraway place, like that hotel in Sweden.
مكان حالم، كذلك الفندق بالسويد.
On this particular evening,
في هذه الليلة بالتحديد،
I came across this live band
صادفت هذه الفرقة الموسيقية الحية
dressed to the T in their coordinating outfits.
التي ترتدي ملابس منسّقة حتى في أدق التفاصيل.
They were floating through the canals
كانوا يعومون في الأقنية المائية
in a large canoe with a fitted-out generator
في قوارب كبيرة مجهزة بمولد
for all of the community to enjoy.
ليستمتع الجميع في المجتمع.
By nightfall, the area becomes almost pitch black,
عند حلول الليل، تصبح المنطقة شبه حالكة السواد،
save for a small lightbulb
ادخر لمصباح صغير
or a fire.
أو نار.
What originally brought me to Makoko
كان الأمر الأساسي الذي جئت إلى ماكوكو لأجله
was this project from a friend of mine,
هو مشروع لصديق لي،
Kunlé Adeyemi, who recently finished building
كونلي أدييمي، الذي كان قد أنهى مؤخراً بناء
this three-story floating school
هذه المدرسة الطافية المكونة من ثلاثة طوابق
for the kids in Makoko.
للأطفال في ماكوكو.
With this entire village existing on the water,
مع وجود هذه القرية بأكملها على الماء،
public space is very limited,
أصبحت المساحة العامة محدودة كثيراً،
so now that the school is finished,
و مع انتهاء المدرسة،
the ground floor is a playground for the kids,
يصبح الطابق الأرضي ملعب للأطفال،
but when classes are out, the platform
لكن مع انتهاء الدوام، تصبح المنصة
is just like a town square,
كساحة للمدينة،
where the fishermen mend their nets
حيث يصلح الصيادون شباكهم
and floating shopkeepers dock their boats.
و يرسي أصحاب المحلات العائمة قواربهم.
Another place I'd like to share with you
مكان آخر أود أن أشاركه معكم
is the Zabbaleen in Cairo.
هو حي الزبّالين في القاهرة.
They're descendants of farmers who began migrating
إنهم أحفاد المزارعين الذين بدأوا بالهجرة
from the upper Egypt in the '40s,
من شمال مصر في الأربعينيات،
and today they make their living
و اليوم هم يجنون قوتهم
by collecting and recycling waste from homes
بتجميع و تدوير النفايات من المنازل
from all over Cairo.
من جميع أنحاء القاهرة.
For years, the Zabbaleen would live in makeshift villages
لسنوات طويلة، يعيش الزبالين في قرى مؤقتة
where they would move around
حيث يغيرون مكانهم باستمرار
trying to avoid the local authorities,
لتجنب السلطات المحلية،
but in the early 1980s, they settled
لكن في أوائل الثمانيات، استقروا
on the Mokattam rocks
على صخور المقطم
just at the eastern edge of the city.
قرب الحدود الشرقية للمدينة.
Today, they live in this area,
اليوم، هم يعيشون في هذا المنطقة،
approximately 50,000 to 70,000 people,
حوالي 50,000 إلى 70,000 شخص،
who live in this community of self-built
الذين يعيشون في هذا المجتمع الذي يحتوي
multi-story houses
على بيوت مبنية ذاتياً مكونة من عدة طوابق
where up to three generations live in one structure.
حيث يعيش حتى الثلاثة أجيال في البناء الواحد.
While these apartments that they built for themselves
بينما تبدو هذه الشقق التي بنوها لأنفسهم
appear to lack any planning or formal grid,
أنها تفتقر إلى أي تخطيط أو شبكة رسمية،
each family specializing in a certain form of recycling
اختصاص كل عائلة بتدوير نوع معين من النفايات
means that the ground floor of each apartment
يعني أن الطابق الأرضي من كل شقة
is reserved for garbage-related activities
محجوز للأنشطة المتعلقة بالنفايات
and the upper floor is dedicated to living space.
و الطابق العلوي مخصص للمعيشة.
I find it incredible to see
إني لأجده أمراً مذهلاً رؤية
how these piles and piles of garbage
كيف تبدو هذه الأكوام و الأكوام من النفاية
are invisible to the people who live there,
و كأنها خفية للأشخاص الذين يعيشون هناك،
like this very distinguished man who is posing
كهذا الرجل المميز جداً الذي يتموضع للصورة
while all this garbage is sort of streaming out behind him,
بينما كل هذه القمامة تبدو و كأنها تتدفق للخارج من ورائه،
or like these two young men who are sitting
أو كهذين الشابين الجالسين
and chatting amongst these tons of garbage.
يتجاذبان أطراف الحديث وسط هذه الأطنان من القمامة.
While to most of us, living amongst
بينما بالنسبة لأغلبنا، قد يبدو
these piles and piles of garbage
العيش بين هذه الأكوام و الأكوام من القمامة
may seem totally uninhabitable,
غير مناسب للسكن كلياً،
to those in the Zabbaleen, this is just
لكنه يعد بالنسبة لأولئك في حي الزبالين، فقط
a different type of normal.
صورة أخرى لما هو طبيعي.
In all these places I've talked about today,
في كل هذه الأماكن التي تحدثت عنها اليوم،
what I do find fascinating is that there's really
ما أجده مثير للإهتمام هو أنه
no such thing as normal,
لا يوجد حقيقةً أي شيء يمكن وصفه بالطبيعي أو العادي.
and it proves that people are able to adapt
و هو يثبت أن الناس قادرة على التأقلم
to any kind of situation.
مع أي نوع من الظروف.
Throughout the day, it's quite common
خلال اليوم، إنه لأمر معتاد
to come across a small party taking place
مصادفة حفلات صغيرة
in the streets, just like this engagement party.
في الشوارع، مثل حفلة الخطوبة هذه.
In this tradition, the bride-to-be
في هذا التقليد، تقوم الزوجة المستقبلية
displays all of their belongings,
بعرض جميع ممتلكاتها،
which they soon bring to their new husband.
التي سوف تصبح قريباً ملك لزوجها.
A gathering like this one
إن اجتماع كهذا
offers such a juxtaposition
يعكس تباين صارخ
where all the new stuff is displayed
حيث يتم عرض كل الأشياء الجديدة
and all the garbage is used
و يتم استخدام كل النفاية
as props to display all their new home accessories.
كدعامات لعرض كل إكسسوارات منزلهم الجديد.
Like Makoko and the Torre David,
كالماكوكو و توري ديفيد،
throughout the Zabbaleen you'll find all
بين حارات الزبالين سوف تجد
the same facilities as in any typical neighborhood.
كل الخدمات الموجودة في أي حي عادي.
There are the retail shops, the cafes
هناك محلات التجزئة، المقاهي
and the restaurants, and the community
و المطاعم، و هذا المجتمع
is this community of Coptic Christians,
هو من المسيحيين الأقباط،
so you'll also find a church,
لذا سوف تجد أيضاً كنيسة،
along with the scores of religious iconographies
بالإضافة إلى عدد كبير من الرموز الدينية
throughout the area,
في المنطقة،
and also all the everyday services
و أيضاً كل الخدمات اليومية
like the electronic repair shops,
مثل محلات تصليح الأجهزة الإلكترونية،
the barbers, everything.
محلات الحلاقة، كل شيء.
Visiting the homes of the Zabbaleen
زيارة بيوت الزبالين
is also full of surprises.
أيضاً مليئة بالمفاجآت.
While from the outside,
بينما من الخارج
these homes look like any other informal structure
تبدو هذه المنازل كأي منشآت عشوائية أخرى
in the city, when you step inside,
في المدينة، لكن عندما تدخلها،
you are met with all manner of design decisions
تجد كل أنواع القرارات في التصميم
and interior decoration.
و التزيين الداخلي.
Despite having limited access to space and money,
على الرغم من قلة المساحة و المال،
the homes in the area are designed
فإن المنازل في المنطقة مصممة
with care and detail.
بتأنّي و تفصيل.
Every apartment is unique,
كل شقة تعد مميزة،
and this individuality tells a story
و هذا الانفراد يحكي قصة
about each family's circumstances and values.
ظروف كل عائلة و قِيَمِها.
Many of these people take their homes
العديد من هؤلاء الناس تأخذ بيوتها
and interior spaces very seriously,
و مساحاتها الداخلية بجدية كبيرة،
putting a lot of work and care
بالعمل كثيراً و بتأنّي
into the details.
على التفاصيل.
The shared spaces are also treated in the same manner,
إن المساحات المشتركة أيضاً تعامل بنفس المعاملة،
where walls are decorated in faux marble patterns.
إن الحوائط مزينة بنقشات رخامية زائفة.
But despite this elaborate decor,
لكن بالرغم من التزيين المفصّل،
sometimes these apartments are used
أحياناً تستعمل هذه الشقق
in very unexpected ways,
بطرق غير متوقعة أبداً،
like this home which caught my attention
مثل هذا المنزل الذي لفت انتباهي
while all the mud and the grass was literally
حيث كان الطين و العشب
seeping out under the front door.
يبرز من أسفل الباب الأمامي.
When I was let in, it appeared that this fifth-floor apartment
عندما دخلت، تبين أن هذه الشقة في الدور الخامس
was being transformed into a complete animal farm,
قد تم تحويلها إلى مزرعة متكاملة،
where six or seven cows stood grazing
حيث كانت هناك ستة أو سبعة أبقار ترعى
in what otherwise would be the living room.
في ما كان ليكون غرفة المعيشة.
But then in the apartment across the hall
لكن في الشقة المقابلة
from this cow shed lives a newly married couple
لزريبة الأبقار هذه يعيش زوجين متزوجين حديثاً
in what locals describe
في شقة يصفها المحليون
as one of the nicest apartments in the area.
بأنها أحد أجمل الشقق في المنطقة.
The attention to this detail astonished me,
إن الانتباه إلى هذا التفصيل قد أبهرني،
and as the owner of the home so proudly
و بينما أخذني المالك بكل فخر
led me around this apartment,
في جولة في هذه الشقة،
from floor to ceiling, every part was decorated.
من الأرض إلى السقف، تم تزيين كل جزء.
But if it weren't for the strangely familiar
لكن لولا الرائحة المألوفة بشكل غريب
stomach-churning odor that constantly
المثيرة للغثيان التي ظلّت
passes through the apartment,
تعبر خلال الشقة،
it would be easy to forget
قد يكون من السهل نسيان
that you are standing next to a cow shed
أنك تقف بجوار زريبة بقر
and on top of a landfill.
و فوق مكب نفايات.
What moved me the most was that despite
أكثر ما أثّر فيني هو أنه بالرغم
these seemingly inhospitable conditions,
من هذه الظروف التي تبدو غير مُرَحِبة،
I was welcomed with open arms
فقد تم الترحيب بي بشدة
into a home that was made with love, care,
إلى منزل صنع بالحب، الرعاية،
and unreserved passion.
و هيام صريح.
Let's move across the map to China,
دعنا نذهب إلى الصين،
to an area called Shanxi, Henan and Gansu.
إلى منطقة تسمى بشانسي، هينان و جانسو.
In a region famous for the soft, porous Loess Plateau soil,
في منطقة تشتهر بتربة هضبة اللوس الطرية، المسامية،
there lived until recently an estimated
لقد عاش هناك حتى مؤخراً
40 million people in these houses underground.
حوالي 40 مليون شخص في هذه البيوت تحت الأرض.
These dwellings are called the yaodongs.
تسمى هذه المساكن بالياودونجس.
Through this architecture by subtraction,
من خلال تقنية الطرح في الهندسة المعمارية،
these yaodongs are built literally inside of the soil.
بنيت هذه الياودونجس حرفياً في داخل التراب.
In these villages, you see an entirely altered landscape,
في هذه القرى، ترى الأرض الطبيعية قد تم تغييرها بالكامل،
and hidden behind these mounds of dirt
و مخبأ وراء هذه التلال من التربة
are these square, rectangular houses
هذه البيوت المربعة، المستطيلة
which sit seven meters below the ground.
على عمق سبعة أمتار من سطح الأرض.
When I asked people why they were digging
عندما سألت الناس لماذا هي تحفر
their houses from the ground,
بيوتها من الأرض،
they simply replied that they are poor wheat
أجابوني ببساطة لأنهم مزارعي
and apple farmers who didn't have the money
قمح و تفاح فقراء و هم لا يمتلكون المال
to buy materials, and this digging out
لشراء المواد، و أن الحفر هذا
was their most logical form of living.
كان أكثر طريقة منطقية للمعيشة.
From Makoko to Zabbaleen, these communities
من ماكوكو إلى الزبالين، هذه المجتمعات
have approached the tasks of planning,
قد قدرت مهام التخطيط،
design and management of their communities
التصميم و إدارة مجتمعاتهم
and neighborhoods in ways that respond
و أحيائهم بطرق تتوافق
specifically to their environment and circumstances.
بالضبط مع بيئاتهم و ظروفهم.
Created by these very people who live,
أنشأها هؤلاء الأشخاص نفسهم الذين عاشوا،
work and play in these particular spaces,
عملوا و لعبوا في هذه المساحات بالذات،
these neighborhoods are intuitively designed
هذه الأحياء المصممة بشكل حدسي
to make the most of their circumstances.
ليستغلوا ظروفهم أفضل استغلال.
In most of these places, the government
في أغلب هذه الأماكن، إن الحكومة
is completely absent, leaving inhabitants
غائبة تماماً، تاركة السكان
with no choice but to reappropriate found materials,
من دون خيار آخر غير إعادة تأهيل المواد الموجودة،
and while these communities are highly disadvantaged,
و بينما تعد هذه المجتمعات فقيرة جداً،
they do present examples
إلّا أنها تقدم أمثلة
of brilliant forms of ingenuity,
لأشكال عبقرية من الابتكار،
and prove that indeed we have the ability
و تثبت أننا حقاً لدينا القدرة
to adapt to all manner of circumstances.
على التكييف مع كل نواحي الظروف.
What makes places like the Torre David
إن ما يجعل أماكن كتوري ديفيد
particularly remarkable
مذهلة بالذات
is this sort of skeleton framework
هو هذا الهيكل العظمي
where people can have a foundation
حيث يجد فيه الناس أساساً
where they can tap into.
يستطيعون الاستفادة منه.
Now imagine what these already ingenious communities
الآن تخيل لو استطاعت هذه المجتمعات
could create themselves,
المبتكرة أصلاً إنشاء أنفسها،
and how highly particular their solutions would be,
و كيف ستكون حلولهم محددة للغاية،
if they were given the basic infrastructures
إن تم توفير لهم البنية التحتية
that they could tap into.
التي يمكنهم الاستفادة منها.
Today, you see these large residential development projects
اليوم، أنتم ترون هذه المشاريع التنموية الكبيرة للسكن
which offer cookie-cutter housing solutions
التي توفر حلولاً للإسكان ذات الإنتاجية العالية
to massive amounts of people.
لعدد هائل من الناس.
From China to Brazil, these projects attempt
من الصين إلى البرازيل، هذه المشاريع تهدف
to provide as many houses as possible,
إلى توفير أكبر عدد ممكن من المنازل،
but they're completely generic
لكنها عامة تماماً
and simply do not work as an answer
و ببساطة لا توفر الحل
to the individual needs of the people.
للحاجات الفردية للناس.
I would like to end with a quote
أود أن أنهي حديثي باقتباس
from a friend of mine and a source of inspiration,
لصديقة و مصدر وحي لي،
Zita Cobb, the founder of the wonderful
زيتا كوب، مُؤَسِسة
Shorefast Foundation,
مُؤسَسة شورفاست،
based out of Fogo Island, Newfoundland.
مقرها جزيرة فوجو، نيوفاوندلاند.
She says that "there's this plague of sameness
إنها تقول أنه &amp;quot;هناك هذا العهد بالتماثل
which is killing the human joy,"
الذي يقتل البهجة الإنسانية،&amp;quot;
and I couldn't agree with her more.
و أنا أوافق تماماً على ذلك.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)